{"tossups": [{"question": "The Cascajal [kas-kah-hal] Block hints at a writing system for this culture. An excavation at this culture\u2019s El Manati site unearthed the Las Limas figure, a prominent example of were-jaguar art. These people were the first to play the \u201cball game,\u201d and their ability to extract latex from nearby trees led them to be known as the \u201crubber people.\u201d For ten points, name this oldest Mesoamerican civilization, known for the construction of large stone heads.", "answer": "<b> Olmec</b> civilization", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A leader of these people named Rollo was granted the Duchy of Normandy by Charles the Simple, while another leader of this group founded the Rurik Dynasty in Russia. Members of this group formed the Great Heathen Army, which invaded the British Isles to avenge the death of Ragnar Lodbrok. These people sacked the monastery of Lindisfarne and sailed to Greenland and Vinland on their longships. For ten points, name these Scandinavian raiders.", "answer": "<b> Viking</b>s (or<b> Norse</b>men; accept<b> Varangian</b>s after \u201cRurik\u201d is said)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A captain of this type of ship, John Worden, was partially blinded in combat from a nearby explosion. John Ericsson designed one of these ships whose wreck was discovered off the coast of Cape Hatteras in 1973 and which mostly floated a foot and a half above the waterline. The USS<em> Cumberland</em> was rammed and sunk by this type of ship, two of which fought to a standstill in the Battle of Hampton Roads. For ten points, name this type of armored ship, exemplified by the<em> Monitor</em> and the<em> Virginia</em>.", "answer": "<b> ironclad</b>s (prompt on descriptive answers about armored ships before said; prompt on Monitor before read; prompt on Virginia or Merrimack before read) Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man was succeeded by Caleb Strong as Governor after the Boston Gazette published Elkanah Tisdale\u2019s cartoon attacking him. This man, along with John Marshall and Charles Pickney, met agents of Talleyrand who demanded a bribe in the XYZ affair. A political cartoon of a dragon representing the unorthodox shape of Essex County lampooned, for ten points, what Massachusetts politician whose name now describes the practice of drawing congressional districts for political gain?", "answer": "Elbridge<b> Gerry</b> (accept<b> gerrymander</b>ing)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This physicist worked with the mathematician Roger Penrose on singularity theory. This man names a type of radiation that occurs due to pair production near the event horizon of a black hole. This Lucasian Professor of Mathematics at Cambridge from 1979 to 2009 was the subject of the 2014 film<em> The Theory</em> <em>of Everything</em>. For ten points, name this British physicist, an expert in black holes and the author of<em> A</em> <em>Brief History of Time</em>.", "answer": "Stephen<b> Hawking</b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "In this country, a duel between Alan Breck and the son of an outlaw is settled by a contest involving musical instruments rather than with weapons. Frank Osbaldistone pursues his cousin to this country in a novel that was admired by this country\u2019s native author, Robert Louis Stevenson. The primary setting of<em> Kidnapped</em> and<em> Rob Roy</em> is, for ten points, what country, the site of the Battle of Culloden during a Jacobite Rising?", "answer": "<b> Scotland</b> (prompt on Great Britain or United Kingdom)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "This state grew out of the territory of Great Moravia and was first ruled by the P\u02d8remyslid Dynasty. The Utraquist religious group in this state negotiated toleration at the Council of Basel. Its ruler was the only king among the electors of the Holy Roman Empire, and it often served as the site of the Empire\u2019s capital city. The Council of Constance condemned a heretic movement in this state led by Jan Hus. A revolt by Protestants in this state started the Thirty Years War. For ten points, name this monarchical Central European state whose capital was Prague.", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Bohemia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man served as Thomas Dewey\u2019s Vice Presidential running mate in 1948, though Dewey famously lost to Truman. Eisenhower initially called this man\u2019s appointment to succeed Fred Vinson a \u201cdamned-fool mistake.\u201d In 1954, this man used the phrase \u201cwith all deliberate speed\u201d in his ruling to desegregate schools in<em> Brown v. Board</em>. For ten points, name this former governor of California who served as the Chief Justice of a notably liberal Supreme Court.", "answer": "Earl<b> Warren</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One possibly apocryphal story about this man states that he fired at enemy troops with a crossbow while lying ill on a stretcher. Before embarking on his most famous campaign, this man put Isaac Komnemnos in chains after a raid on Cyprus. This man was victorious at the battle of Arsuf and managed to anger Leopold V of Austria during the siege of Acre, who later imprisoned him. After failing to conquer Jerusalem, this man was forced to negotiate peace with Saladin. For ten points, name this English leader of the Third Crusade, whose nickname refers to his bravery.", "answer": "<b> Richard I</b> or<b> Richard the Lionheart</b>ed", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This waterway is named after a kingdom that was absorbed by Portugal in 1914. Upstream of the Boyoma Falls, this river is known as the Lualaba, and a planned dam along</b> <b>its (+)</b> <b>Inga Falls would be the largest hydroelectric project in the world. A widening of</b> <b>this waterway known as the Malebo Pool has two national capitals along its banks. A set of rapids along this river is named after an explorer who was sought by Henry Morton (*) </b>Stanley, David Livingstone. The national capitals of Kinshasa and Brazzaville are on the banks of, for ten points, what second-longest river in Africa?", "answer": "<b> Congo</b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>James Madison vetoed this man\u2019s proposed 1817 Bonus Bill. As Secretary of War under James Monroe, this man created the Bureau of Indian Affairs. This man\u2019s involvement in</b> <b>the (+)</b> <b>Petticoat Affair led to his resignation as vice president. As a senator, he rejected</b> <b>the Compromise of 1850, claimed slavery was a \u201cpositive good,\u201d and was a chief advocate for states\u2019 rights during (*)</b> the nullification crisis. For ten points, name this member of the Senate\u2019s\u201cGreat Triumvirate,\u201d a senator from South Carolina.", "answer": "John Caldwell<b> Calhoun</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A Supreme Court case arising from this U.S. state debated the validity of a December 12th \u201csafe harbor\u201d deadline. Republicans operatives were flown into this state to cause the</b> <b>Brooks Brothers Riot. (+)</b> <b>Katherine Harris served as its Secretary of State during an</b> <b>election marked by awkward \u201cbutterfly (*)</b> ballots,\u201d which may have caused this state\u2019s voters to mark their ballots for Pat Buchanan instead of Al Gore. For ten points, name this state whose 25 electoral votes clinched the 2000 Presidential election for George W. Bush, the brother of its Governor, Jeb.", "answer": "<b> Florida</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This artist created several multicolored versions of an electric chair in Sing Sing prison, as well as images from newspapers of a race riot and car crashes, in his</b><em><b> Death and</b></em><b> (+) </b><em><b>Disaster Series</b></em><b>. He used the technique of screen-printing to create multiple copies of his subjects, working in a studio called the Factory. A series of 32 canvases by this artist includes (*) </b> flavors like<em> Onion</em> and<em> Split Pea</em>. For ten points, name this Pop artist of the<em> Marilyn Diptych</em> and <em>Campbell\u2019s Soup Cans</em>.", "answer": "Andy<b> Warhol</b> (or Andy<b> Warhola</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One person who held this title reduced his army to the size of three hundred men and routed the Midianites using trumpets and clay jars. Another of these leaders repeatedly defeated the Philistines, but lost his (+) uncut hair and committed suicide by toppling the temple of Dagon. (*)</b> Deborah is the only female holder of this title named in the Bible. Gideon and Samson were among, for ten points, what Israelite rulers whose history is recounted in the seventh book of the Bible?", "answer": "Biblical<b> judges</b> (accept<b> Judges</b> of Israel, Old Testament<b> judges</b>, and other elaborations that use the word<b> judge</b>; accept<b> shofet</b> or<b> shoftim</b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b>This man was the subject of the Rettig Report, commissioned by his successor, Patricio Aylwin. This man formed Codelco by consolidating his country\u2019s copper mining industry,</b> <b>and he oversaw a period of economic revival due to the reforms of the (+)</b> <b>Chicago Boys.</b> <b>This man initiated an effort to execute political prisoners known as the Caravan of Death and took part in a (*) </b> CIA-sponsored effort to support right-wing dictatorships called Operation Condor. For ten points, name this ruler of Chile who, in 1973, overthrew Salvador Allende [ah-yen-day].", "answer": "Augusto<b> Pinochet</b> [pin-oh-shay]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}